Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Majesty.
Noble Consort Lumière has been waiting inside for some time.
Call for Noble Prince Guo to wait here.
He must not enter until I summon him.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has returned.
Why does Your Majesty...
look at me like that?
When did it begin?
Pardon my slow-wittedness.
I don't know what Your Majesty refers to.
I've doted on you all these years.
But in this moment,
I truly resent your face.
I was reminded today of Emperor Yuan, who
married off his concubine Zhaojun to the west.
Galdan said it?
Galdan requested an audience with me.
He asked for a marriage alliance - to marry you.
How did you catch his eye?
I'm Your Majesty's concubine.
How can I abase myself in a marriage alliance?
Galdan is truly absurd!
Of course I know he is.
I said as much to him, to silence him.
But he cited the precedent of Emperor Yuan of Han,
and compared you to Zhaojun.
He asked me to relinquish my love.
Your face is alluring to me,
and so it can also allure others.
I shouldn't have allowed you to meet him.
Sending Zhaojun beyond the frontier
led to lifelong aching for Emperor Yuan.
I am Your Majesty's concubine.
If this happens,
our children will hang their heads in shame
for the rest of their lives.
He told me he doesn't care about any of these things.
He'll do whatever is required to obtain what he likes -
let alone his desire for you!
If I'm the cause of Galdan's evil desires,
I'd rather destroy my looks to save my face.
It's not only a matter of face.
Although the plague has won the Great Qing
some time to defend against the Dzungars,
there's no guarantee that they won't find a cure.
Moreover, these continuous wars have
greatly depleted the Great Qing's strength.
I've consulted the Ministry of Revenue.
Even if we garner all our supplies,
they will support the army for only three to five months.
Continuing in this deadlock
will do us "no good but a hundred harms."
Galdan told me unequivocally
that as long as I approve you becoming his Consort,
and give him the remedy for the plague,
he will wholly recall the Dzungar army.
And every year from now on,
they'll take only a hundred thousand silver taels
and food supplies for three thousand troops,
and will never again cause
the Great Qing's beacon towers to be lit.
Now I understand, Your Majesty.
I hold the position of Noble Consort
and have been favored by Your Majesty for years.
The time has come to repay Your Majesty's heavenly grace.
I dare not selfishly cherish my own being.
I will abide by Your Majesty's wishes.
I'm the ruler of a nation.
But this...
this is for you to decide.
I dare not forget Your Majesty's grace.
- Your Noble Highness, please reconsider!
- Your Lordship! Your Lordship!
It can't be this way!
Even though Your Noble Highness can set your own well-being aside,
Your Majesty's reputation for justice will be questioned.
Your Lordship, His Majesty has not summoned you.
You cannot enter like this.
Su Peisheng.
Let Noble Prince Guo finish, or he'll feel disregarded.
Your Lordship is overthinking.
This is my own volition.
His Majesty hasn't forced me.
Surely Your Highness doesn't want to
create difficulties for His Majesty.
If Your Highness enters into this marriage alliance,
His Majesty will be like Emperor Yuan,
"the laughingstock of posterity."
Then how shall I respond to Galdan?
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Lumière has a
distinguished status as the mother of three children.
If Her Highness is sent off to a marriage alliance,
what will Your Majesty tell the Princes and Princesses
when they ask about their mother?
Also,
The Dzungar Khanate is thousands of miles away.
When Your Majesty misses Noble Consort Lumière in the future,
you might not be able to see her again.
Your Majesty adores Her Noble Highness,
and surely doesn't want her to suffer
a life spent pacifying the frontier tribes.
If the Dzungars want a marriage alliance,
what if Your Majesty seeks someone else
with talent and beauty to marry Galdan?
This will protect Her Noble Highness,
and also save face for Galdan.
You know that
the devotion of one's heart is extremely
difficult to change.
Since he dared to ask for Noble Consort Lumière,
he must have his heart set on her.
Do you think
sending someone else will satisfy Galdan
enough to back down?
Your service is not needed here. You may go now.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Whether it is Noble Consort Lumière or someone else,
this is sacrificing a woman's life to protect our homeland.
What difference does it make?
If the Dzungars use this as a precedent
and request a marriage alliance every year,
won't all women under Heaven be persecuted?
Where is the dignity of the Great Qing?
I don't think it is a proper decision, Your Majesty.
I was blindsided,
not even noticing when Noble Consort Lumière
caught Galdan's eye.
Now, I am already deep in this dilemma
and have lost all dignity.
Your Majesty, it's not that we can't defeat the Dzungars!
Do you think I can ...
bear to give away Noble Consort Lumière?
It's not that we cannot fight,
but we cannot be fighting wars like this forever.
In the current situation,
how many capable generals do you think we still have?
The most foolish tactic in the Han Dynasty's history
was the marriage alliance.
If Your Majesty doesn't despise my incompetence,
I will lead troops to the frontier
and not return until the Dzungars are defeated!
Tell me,
is your request made for the Great Qing,
or for her?
Your Majesty has gone through so much trouble
just to hear me say this.
You have always been humble and cautious.
But when you heard I approved marrying off
Noble Consort Lumière,
you recklessly burst into the hall.
You rarely pay attention to state affairs,
and you know that I dislike having princes lead the military.
But for her,
you request to lead troops against the Dzungars.
I blame only myself for my blindness,
not seeing the affair between the two of you!
Your Majesty is mistaken!
Had you not recklessly burst into the hall today,
I would never believe what I was told -
that you two had met privately outside the palace!
It was my fault for being oblivious.
And you....
Very well!
Your Majesty!
Noble Consort Lumière always respectfully
follows palace protocol.
I was being reckless.
Barging into the hall was most inappropriate.
But I am a son of the Great Qing!
I cannot bear to see the Great Qing
coerced and humiliated by the Dzungars!
Although I am incompetent,
I receive stipends as a Noble Prince
and must devote my entire life to the country!
Keep going.
I understand Your Majesty may have presumptions,
but that's because Your Majesty cares so
exceedingly for Noble Consort Lumière.
This is due to Your Noble Highness's merit.
Over the past years
I have heard quite a bit of idle talk,
saying that ever since you married Lord Consort Yuyin,
you two have been at odds with each other.
Even Your Majesty is troubled by the affairs in the harem.
You can surely understand my difficulties
between Yuyin and Jingxian.
Deep affection gives rise to jealousy,
and intense jealousy leads to suspicion.
Disharmony comes from the deepest care.
In fact, the greatest danger for a couple is suspicion.
I'm not afraid to endure humiliation
for the sake of the Great Qing.
But with the previous incident with Dr. Wen,
and today's matter implicating His Lordship,
My heart cannot help but feel as cold as ashes.
Cold as ashes?
I had a moment of doubt in my mind.
Yunli married Yuyin because of the cutout paper portrait.
The portrait did resemble Yuyin.
But it could also be said to resemble you.
I don't dare to think further.
Your Majesty is overthinking.
I am thinking too much indeed.
Whether it was Noble Consort Lumière's intention or not,
her presence created a rift between us brothers
and attracted covetousness from an outsider.
She is trouble like "an ominous flood."
I will grant Galdan's request,
and send her away from the Great Qing.
I approve of the marriage alliance with the Dzungars.
Please reconsider, Your Majesty!
My mind is made up, and will not be changed.
"At the spring banquet,"
"a cup of green wine is raised and a song is sung."
"I bow and bow to express my three wishes:"
"May my husband live for a thousand years;"
"May this humble wife remain ever healthy;"
"May we be like the returning swallows on the wooden beams,"
"meeting each other year after year."
I was a banished concubine.
Today I can put my meager self to use,
however little, for Your Majesty;
I will devote myself with no doubts.
Even though I will not be able to meet Your Majesty year after year,
I will pray for Your Majesty's longevity and eternal health.
You may leave now.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Let me ask you this:
You have agreed to the marriage alliance.
How will you conduct yourself?
I dare not endure
any humiliation...
that would tarnish Your Majesty's reputation.
I am not Emperor Yuan,
nor do I want you to be another Zhaojun
that never returns.
Even if my seventeenth brother
has any improper intentions toward you,
I will not truly hold a grudge against him.
"Love for beauty is only human."
It is understandable that they covet your beauty.
However,
no matter how much others admire your beauty,
your heart can only belong to me.
His Majesty issued an edict last night
saying my sister is gravely ill
and visiting her is forbidden.
Claiming an illness, and also forbidding visitors -
this is no different than confining her.
It seems that His Majesty is intending
to proceed with the marriage alliance.
As soon as Noble Consort Lumière passes the border,
His Majesty will announce her death.
She will be... no more.
What an inconvenience that we're here in the Summer Palace.
If your source is reliable,
we must first return home and then make a careful plan.
His Majesty will also return to the palace in a day or two.
Let's go right away.
I wish I knew how he has been.
Your Highness still cares about Lord XVII
even when you are confined and kept in the dark.
I'm afraid Yunli may lose control of his temper.
Yesterday, when I bid farewell to His Majesty,
I was not wishing for His Majesty's longevity,
but instead hoping Yunli will not lose his composure again, because of me.
I don't mind what would happen to me,
but I can't let him be another victim.
His Majesty...
is so cruel-hearted.
"Burnished until the complexion is lustrous as jade,
and sold to the imperial house."
Even my life is held in His Majesty's hands.
The supposed "favor and affection"
cannot compare to the future of the nation and the peace of society.
Had I asked His Majesty for his pity and protection,
I would have truly overvalued my worth.
I see Your Highness... plans to give up on yourself.
His Majesty already has suspicions.
Between Yunli and I, one of us cannot be saved.
Instead of him, I'd rather it be me.
Your Highness must not have such somber thoughts.
If he dies,
no one from his household will be able to survive.
But if I die,
His Majesty, in the end, will consider the children
and will not try to eliminate all of them.
And what makes you think
that if he dies, I can continue to live?
But if misfortune befalls Your Highness,
His Lordship will also feel the same.
And so
I'll do my utmost to preserve what I can.
[The "double happiness" character, symbol of marriage]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Your Lordship!
You can't go.
I have decided.
Your Lordship,
His Majesty's suspicions are deeply rooted.
After so many years of forbearance,
why risk yourself at this critical juncture?
You know the reason. No need to ask more.
Your Lordship,
do you care so much for Elder Sister
that you don't care for your own life?
To protect me, she offered to sacrifice herself.
I would do the same.
But she wasn't protecting you!
She was protecting herself!
Refusing the marriage alliance would only lead to her death
while accepting it may give her a chance to live.
Your Lordship, don't you know how she is?
Back then, as soon as she heard of your death,
she returned to the palace.
Why do you still want to give up your
safety and status for her?
We both had our difficulties back then.
Speak no more.
I never measure actions between Huan'er and myself.
If anything happens to her,
I will never forgive myself my entire life.
Your Lordship!
I have never begged you for anything.
This time I am begging you...
I'm begging you with my life.
Please don't go.
She is my elder sister,
and I am in debt for her kindness,
but you are my husband
and the only man I have loved in my life.
I would rather hurt anyone else
than allow you to be hurt.
Yuyin,
I know I have been unfair to you
but I can't heed you in this.
Even if you bring her back,
will His Majesty spare you both?
Wake up, Your Lordship!
Since the moment my eyes first beheld her,
I knew such a day would come.
Even if I can't save myself,
I must save her.
Your Majesty.
Is everything taken care of?
Everything is proceeding well.
The word has been spread.
Noble Prince Guo will believe that Noble Consort Lumière
has been sent away for the marriage alliance.
Good.
No one knows
that in the wedding sedan,
lies only the prescription to treat the plague.
How audacious of Galdan
to disrespect Heaven's Empire by proposing
marriage to Noble Consort Lumière.
"Those who accomplish greatness are not bothered by trifles".
Nor are they fixated on romantic feelings.
I told him I would only send him the remedy for the plague,
and he understood this limit.
But Galdan denied the affair between
Noble Prince Guo and Noble Consort Lumière.
I was not blind to Galdan's intention to protect her -
driven by his own affection.
Noble Prince Guo bears the blame.
He dared to covet Your Majesty's woman.
This is disloyalty to his monarch.
I know you are good at what you do.
Now we will see if Yunli pursues
Noble Consort Lumière to the border.
If he does,
that's the proof that he indeed covets my woman.
I'll have my people watch Noble Consort Lumière
and make sure no news leaks out.
Good.
Galdan has left the capital.
Announce my decree: we return to the palace tomorrow.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Seventeenth brother, leave free of concerns.
Yurao and I will not give away any information.
You can cover for me for a while, but not forever.
You're implicated after all.
Seventeenth brother, please take good care of yourself.
Brothers, you are all my personal guards.
The trip to the frontier is fraught with danger.
There is a chance that I may not return.
But still I ask you to aid me with all your strength.
I am selfish... to put you in this situation.
We are willing to follow Your Lordship.
We will disregard life or death
and give our utmost to protect our lord!
Your Majesty.
What happened?
It has been reported that
Lord XVII has left the capital, leading his mounted guards.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Imperial Father.
Rise.
Longyue has grown taller.
Come here. Let Imperial Father look at you.
Go.
What's wrong?
The princess seems to have some grown-up worries.
She heard that Hongyan and Lingxi fell ill,
and kept asking to go and visit them.
She has been heavyhearted since we returned,
unable to eat or sleep well.
I visited Lingxi and Hongyan.
The doctors said their illness was caused
by Spleen-Stomach Disharmony and somber thoughts.
How can such small children have somber thoughts?
It must be due to the servants' ineptitude.
I've already criticized their nursemaids.
Hongyan and Lingxi haven't seen Mother for a long time.
They must be missing her terribly.
I heard Mother has been too sick to get out of bed.
I cannot comfort my younger brother and sister,
or care for Mother at her bedside.
That's why I am sad.
Estime and the other mothers
treat you well and lovingly.
I know.
I was reading Mencius yesterday.
Mencius said, "The person of virtue has three joys,
but to rule over a kingdom is not one of them."
"That his parents are alive and his siblings are at peace; this is one joy."
"Facing Heaven, he bears no shame; facing his fellow men, he carries no guilt. This is the second joy."
"Guiding and educating all talented individuals
under Heaven; this is the third joy."
I hope to become a person of virtue.
I'll be filial to Imperial Father and my Mother,
and take good care of my brother and sister.
Is there anything bothering Your Majesty?
You haven't been able to sleep well these days.
Nothing. You should go to sleep.
Noble Consort Lumière has been convalescing
at the Verdant Reading Hall.
Since Your Majesty is worried about her,
why not bring her back to the palace?
I know Your Majesty cares for Lumière very much.
Go to sleep.
Although His Majesty allowed
Your Highness to return to the palace,
the matter of Lord XVII pursuing Your Highness
to the border isn't over yet.
I'm afraid that His Majesty will still
question Your Highness about it.
Even though he has allowed me back,
The Palace of Eternal Longevity is empty.
There's not even a ghost here.
Everyone thinks that I'm still in the Summer Palace.
If I died now
would anyone know?
His Majesty certainly wants to
hear Your Highness's explanation.
That's why he requested you see him tomorrow
in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Your Highness should be prepared.
Your Majesty, Noble Consort Lumière is here.
Your Majesty, I have recovered from my illness
and come to pay my respects.
Your illness was not a serious concern.
But it made Noble Prince Guo believe
you had left for the marriage alliance.
He led troops to the border without permission.
Noble Consort Lumière,
his affection for you is truly deep.
Your Majesty, I deserve to die ten thousand times
for my ignorance of this.
You deserve death indeed.
Do you have anything else to say for yourself?
Noble Prince Guo left for the border recklessly
with the intent to protect the Great Qing's dignity.
However, I was the root of the incident
I am willing to accept any punishment from Your Majesty.
Of course I'll punish you.
I will humbly obey the decree of Heaven.
It's not just this matter that I want to punish you for.
But to punish you for several offenses at once,
I don't even know where to start.
I see you have grown thinner.
I assume that you continuously
"reflected on yourself facing a wall" in the Summer Palace.
All right. Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Take Noble Consort Lumière back to her palace.
Yes.
Go see your children.
They missed you very much during those days you were ill.
I take my leave.
Mother, you have fully recovered.
Your Highness.
Go pay respects to your Father.
Yes.
Your Majesty, would you like
some almond tea to soothe your throat?
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Will my forgiveness of Noble Consort Lumière
make her feel conceited?
Your Majesty, please forgive me for saying something I shouldn't.
This matter was not Her Noble Highness's fault.
It was Yunli's fault.
He coveted an imperial consort
and left the capital without permission.
Rebellion is a treasonous offense.
Noble Prince Guo wouldn't dare to betray Your Majesty.
Yunli has already submitted a memorandum,
admitting the offense of commanding troops
without permission.
He requests to guard the border and be punished
by the hardships of the wind and sand.
It's just as well if His Lordship does not come back,
so as not to displease Your Majesty.
You know nothing!
If I punish him for this, it will spur idle gossip,
speculating about the affairs in the palace.
He asked for punishment, but I'll reward him instead.
Announce my decree:
Noble Prince Guo and Venerable Prince Shen
showed their loyalty in defending the country.
I hereby promote Noble Prince Guo to State Prince Guo,
and Venerable Prince Shen to Noble Prince Shen.
State Prince Guo will be stationed outside the Yanming Pass.
Unless summoned, he cannot return to the capital.
Yes, Your Majesty.
[Three years later]
[“This night brings a full moon and blooming flowers.
May my beloved and I eternally abide in a peaceful life.”]
Blooming flowers and a full moon are easy to find,
but a peaceful life with one's beloved cannot last.
Huan'er, at this moment,
I hope you are safe and happy under the same moonlight.
Are these letters reliable?
Have you confirmed they're not written by someone else?
Yes, Your Majesty.
When I paid my respects to Lord Consort Yu,
I secretly obtained them
from the bottom drawer of her dressing table.
Are all the letters here?
I only took these so that they wouldn't notice.
How's State Prince Guo doing?
Your Majesty, in the three years State Prince Guo
has guarded the Yanming Pass,
there has not been a single violation from the Dzungars.
His Lordship guards the border with rigorous discipline.
He lives and dines alongside the soldiers
without growing conceited due to his rank.
He is obeyed and admired by all the officers and soldiers.
Is he trying to win their hearts over?
I presume His Lordship doesn't want to provide
reasons for criticism.
I've read his memorandum.
It quotes a poem that says
"the spring breeze does not blow through the Yumen Pass".
He emphasized the coldness
and the hardship of the borderlands,
and asked me to show generosity for the soldiers
and citizens living there.
He proposed to re-establish mutual trade
so that the people can enjoy a peaceful and prosperous life.
His Lordship's suggestions are reasonable.
Even so, there is no need for him to say more than he should.
I sent him to guard the border,
not to impose his opinion on state affairs.
Your Majesty should refrain from anger.
The imperial doctors advised that anger can counteract
the medicine Your Majesty has been taking.
It's been three years.
Summon him back to the capital to report on his work.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Mother, look! Dragonflies! Red dragonflies!
Lingxi, look over there.
The lotus has bloomed in the lake.
Why are there lotus flowers in the lake
but no other flowers?
It's because...
The scent of lotus flowers is already refreshing by itself.
If there were other flowers, it would disrupt the aroma.
Lingxi, this is your seventeenth uncle.
Greetings, Seventeenth Uncle.
Lingxi has grown up so much.
I heard that Your Lordship was coming back,
but I didn't expect it to be so soon.
I haven't returned to the capital for a long time.
I hurried on the road day and night.
My anxious heart wished to fly as fast as an arrow.
I haven't seen Your Noble Highness for a long time.
I trust you have been well.
Thanks to Your Lordship's blessing,
all is well.
Have you seen Yuyin and Yuanchen since you got back?
I came in a hurry to report to His Majesty.
I haven't had a chance to go home.
I will quickly arrange for them to be brought over here.
The winds and frost are bitter at the borderland.
Every time Yuyin mentioned it,
we were all deeply worried for you.
I thank Your Noble Highness for your concern.
I have been writing letters to Yuyin all this time
to lessen her worries and concerns.
Your Lordship.
I've finally found you.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Peace to Your Lordship.
Your Lordship, His Majesty is expecting you.
His Majesty has been kept waiting
and is growing worried.
Please hurry, Your Lordship.
I'll go right away.
His Majesty cherishes his brotherhood with His Lordship
and sent me to come look for him.
Here.
Seventeenth brother.
I need a word of truth.
Three years in the harsh winds at the borderland,
who did you miss the most?
My mother.
Your Majesty,
I am an unfilial son.
You dared to lead troops out of the capital without permission.
Did you remember your mother then?
I still have filial piety,
just as Your Majesty does.
Your Majesty is a wise emperor,
and surely won't blame my mother and Yuyin
for a fault of my own.
Out. All out.
Seventeenth brother.
Tell me the truth.
Did you and Noble Consort Lumière have an illicit affair?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support or join us: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.